<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<!--                                                              -->
<!--                         WHAT IS ADA                          -->
<!--                                                              -->
<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<section id="About_ADA" xreflabel="Top of the Section">
  <title>About ADA</title>

  <qandaset defaultlabel="qanda">
    <qandaentry id="whatisada">
      <question>
        <para>What is ADA?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>
          ADA is a tool that provides support for <quote>Agile and Distributed
          Authoring</quote>. Authors usually use a combination of tools to
          produce documents. The actual variety of documents makes more
          appropriate to refer to this items as resources. A resource may be a
          regular text document, but it may also be a screen capture, video
          clip, audio clip, picture, etc. ADA is conceived to manipulate
          resources in this context.
        </para>
        <para>
          The challenge appears when a large set of resources with a complex
          structure is created by a large number of authors working in a
          distributed environment.
        </para>

        <para>
          The first problem is the variety of tools used by the authors. ADA
          facilitates the post-processing by automatically producing
          preliminary versions of the created resources. The following figure
          illustrates a generic authoring environment and the support provided
          by ADA.
        </para>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/AuthorEnv.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Author environment and ADA role</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <para>
          Once created, the exported resources can be sent to a location where
          they are automatically combined to produce the final resource. The
          following figure illustrates a scenario combining these two aspects.
        </para>
        
        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Kitchen.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Combining resources with ADA</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <para>
          ADA offers support in two steps of this procedure.
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              To the author: ADA provides rules to automate typical processing
              steps to achieve an approximate appearance of the created
              resources. Authors may then focus on the content and verify,
              using these rules, that the final resource complies with certain
              minimum requirements (guidelines, size, quality, etc.)
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              In the production phase: ADA allows specifying a set of rules to
              automatically combine all the contributions from different
              authors and produce a complex resource.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>
          The main element for ADA in the author working directory is the rule
          file. This file has the name <filename>Properties.txt</filename>
          (although it can be changed) and specifies which are the resource
          files and how they need to be processed to obtain the final
          resources. Each working directory needs a file with the rules
          applying to the files contained in it.
        </para>

        <para>Back to <xref linkend="About_ADA"/>.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry id="whatisnotada">
      <question>
        <para>What ADA is not?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>
          ADA is not a text editor, nor a graphic editor, nor an integrated
          creative environment. The author may use tools to create the
          resources, and ADA is used to automatically combine them into a
          global creation process.
        </para>

        <para>
          To use an analogy, ADA offers a very efficient courier service that,
          if you comply with certain requirements when creating resources, it
          takes them very quickly to the assembling plant, combines them with
          other resources contributed by other authors and automatically
          creates a final resource.
        </para>

        <para>Back to <xref linkend="About_ADA"/>.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="whyisadaneeded">
      <question>
        <para>Why is ADA needed?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>
          ADA is oriented toward reducing the creation/modification cycle of a
          set of resources with a non-trivial organization. In the information
          era, the creation process is changing radically. Authors are no
          longer required to use a concrete tool, but instead, certain formats
          are used to easily publish content. But what really takes a
          multi-user distributed authoring scenario to a new dimension is a
          <emphasis>simple modification cycle</emphasis>. Think Wikipedia, its
          distributed authoring paradigm has consolidated beyond any doubt,
          but in order for those authors to contribute effectively, resources
          are extremely easy to modify.
        </para>

        <para>
          A typical situation when a number of authors contribute toward a
          common resource is illustrated in the following figure. There is
          usually an entity that absorbs the complexity of providing a
          homogeneous view of the material usually through an expensive and
          time consuming production stage. This production requires then an
          additional step to bring all the material to the final web
          publishing platform.
        </para>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/AuthorCycle.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Conventional authoring cycle</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <para>
          The following picture illustrates the change in methodology that can
          be achieved with the help of ADA. By providing a fast two-way
          information channel between creation and production, the management
          of a set of resources can be truly improved. ADA provides the rules
          that automatically connect the source documents with the final
          published resources such that changes can be performed at a very
          low turnaround cost.
        </para>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/AuthorNewCycle.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Conventional authoring cycle</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        
        <para>
          But aside from the turnaround time for changes, resources tend to be
          built hierarchically from the multiple sources. The internal
          organization of a resource can be often replicated in the process in
          which it is built. For example, to create the electronic version of
          a book, there is certain amount of work that can be done for each
          chapter individually accompanied by certain inter-chapter
          processing. The rules defined in ADA are prepared to be applied
          hierarchically at different points of the overall production
          procedure. The following picture illustrates a hypothetical scenario
          in which a resource is built by combining resources from four
          authors in three gradual stages.
        </para>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ProductionCycle.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Full production cycle with ADA</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <para>Back to <xref linkend="About_ADA"/>.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>
  </qandaset>
</section>

