<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
  Copyright (C) 2008 Carlos III University of Madrid
  This file is part of Adagio: Agile Distributed Authoring Integrated Toolkit

  This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
  modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
  as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
  of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
  GNU General Public License for more details.

  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
  along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
  Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

-->
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<!--                                                              -->
<!--                         WHAT IS Adagio                       -->
<!--                                                              -->
<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<section id="About_Adagio" xreflabel="Top of the Section">
  <title>About Adagio</title>

  <qandaset>
    <qandaentry id="whatisadagio">
      <question>
        <para>What is Adagio?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>Adagio is a toolkit to integrate the <quote>Agile and Distributed
        Authoring</quote> of web material. The ideal scenario for the tool is a
        set of authors each of them producing a large number of web resources
        that require a significant amount of post-processing. These authors
        share a common working area divided into multiple sub-areas where the
        resources are designed. Adagio allows the definition of rules to
        assemble and produce a set of resources suitable to be published on the
        net.</para>

        <para>The challenge in this scenario is to be able to deal with a large
        number of different resources, organized in a non-trivial structure and
        allow for efficient distributed work.</para>

        <para>Adagio facilitates content production by offering a set of
        pre-defined rules that automatically process the source files of a
        resource to obtain the version to be published in the net. The following
        figure gives an overview of the authoring environment and the support
        provided by Adagio.</para>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/AuthorEnv.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Author environment and ADA role</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <para>In each folder, a file is included containing the set of
        pre-defined rules that need to be executed to create the appropriate
        resources. The rules allow also the combination of resources from
        multiple directories in a hierarchical structure to finally obtain a
        final project suitable to be published. The following figure illustrates
        a scenario where resources are combined to obtain the set of resources
        to be published.</para>
        
        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Kitchen.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Combining resources with Adagio</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <para>Adagio offers support in two steps of this production flow.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>To the author: Adagio defines rules to automate content
            production from source files. As a consequence, authors may focus
            mostly on content and leave the external appearance and overall
            structure to be created automatically. The set of pre-defined rules
            are deployed such that they apply to a large set of resources at the
            same time.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>In the production phase: Adagio allows the description of a
            hierarchical production flow that automatically assembles a large
            web-site from the multiple resources available in a
            repository.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The main Adagio element in the author working directory is the so
        called <emphasis>rule file</emphasis>. This file has the name
        <filename>Properties.dgo</filename> (although it can be changed) and
        contains the set of rules and the order in which they need to be
        executed to obtain the final version of the resources.</para>

	<para>For example: suppose you have several Word documents, images and
	HTML pages spread across several folders. From these resources you want
	to publish a set of documents such that Word documents are translated to
	PDF format, HTML pages are enhanced with some CSS styles, and the images
	are translated from their original format to PNG. These transformations
	can be done once at the begining of your project, but typically, as the
	project evolves, changes are required in the original documents, and the
	production phase needs to be repeated several times. Adagio offers the
	possibility of executing automatically a set of pre-defined rules that
	make the production phase transparent allowing authors to work directly
	over the source documents without worrying about how all parts are
	assembled to create the set of publishable resources.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry id="whatisnotadagio">
      <question>
        <para>What Adagio is not?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>Adagio is not a text editor, nor a graphic editor, nor an
        integrated creative environment. The author must use auxiliary tools to
        create the resources. Adagio is used to automatically combine them by
        executing the production rules and create a global repository.</para>

        <para>To use an analogy, Adagio offers a very efficient courier service
        that, if you comply with certain requirements when creating resources,
        it takes them very quickly to the assembling plant, combines them with
        other resources contributed by other authors and automatically creates a
        final collection of resources suitable to be published.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>
    <qandaentry id="whyisadagioneeded">
      <question>
        <para>Why is Adagio needed?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>Adagio is oriented toward reducing the creation/modification cycle
        of a set of resources with a non-trivial organization. In the
        information era, the creation process is changing radically. Authors are
        no longer required to use a concrete tool, but instead, certain formats
        are used to easily publish content. But what really takes a multi-user
        distributed authoring scenario to a new dimension is a <emphasis>simple
        modification cycle</emphasis>. Think Wikipedia, its distributed
        authoring paradigm has consolidated beyond any doubt, but in order for
        those authors to contribute effectively, resources are extremely easy to
        modify.</para>

        <para>A typical situation when a number of authors contribute toward a
          common resource is illustrated in the following figure. There is
          usually an entity that absorbs the complexity of providing a
          homogeneous view of the material usually through an expensive and
          time consuming production stage. This production requires then an
          additional step to bring all the material to the final web
          publishing platform.</para>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/AuthorCycle.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Conventional authoring cycle</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <para>The following picture illustrates the change in methodology that
        can be achieved with the help of Adagio. By providing a fast two-way
        information channel between creation and production, the management of a
        set of resources can be truly improved. Adagio provides the rules that
        automatically connect the source documents with the final published
        resources such that changes can be performed at a very low turnaround
        cost.</para>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/AuthorNewCycle.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Conventional authoring cycle</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
        
        <para>But aside from the turnaround time for changes, resources tend to
        be built hierarchically from the multiple sources. The internal
        organization of a resource can be often replicated in the process in
        which it is built. For example, to create the electronic version of a
        book, there is certain amount of work that can be done for each chapter
        individually accompanied by certain inter-chapter processing. The rules
        defined in Adagio are prepared to be applied hierarchically at different
        points of the overall production procedure. The following picture
        illustrates a hypothetical scenario in which a resource is built by
        combining resources from four authors in three gradual stages.</para>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ProductionCycle.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Full production cycle with Adagio</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>
  </qandaset>
</section>

