<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
  Copyright (C) 2008 Carlos III University of Madrid
  This file is part of the ADA: Agile Distributed Authoring Toolkit

  This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
  modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
  as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
  of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
  GNU General Public License for more details.

  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
  along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
  Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

-->
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<!--                                                              -->
<!--                          CLEANING                            -->
<!--                                                              -->
<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<section id="Cleaning_Files">
  <title>Cleaning files produced by ADA</title>

  <qandaset>
    <qandaentry id="cleaning">
      <question>
        <para>How to clean the files produced by the ADA rules?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>The rules used by ADA to create resources are prepared to be
	invoked to <emphasis>clear</emphasis> the produced files. This step is
	useful to start from scratch in the production of resources, or simply
	to reduce the content of a directory only to the source files.</para>

	<para>Each rule used in ADA to produce a resource has its equivalent to
	remove it. Thus, with no additional information in the
	<filename>Properties.txt</filename> file, by simply executing the
	command <code>adado clean</code>, all the production rules are invoked
	again, although this time to remove the produced resources.</para>

	<para>ADA performs this cleaning procedure by <quote>deducing</quote>
	the file names of the produced resources through the given
	definitions. If you plan to change these definitions, the recommended
	procedure is first to <quote>clean</quote> the directory, change the
	file names and then apply again the rules. If the names of the produced
	files are changed and there are some of these old files in the
	directory, the execution of the cleaning procedure with the new
	properties will not remove them, the author will have to do it by
	hand.</para>

	<para>Although ADA knows exactly the files that creates, there are some
	special cases in which the cleaning rule does not remove everything that
	was created. The exception are the empty directories. If a production
	rule creates new files in a directory, and eventually the directory
	itself, when cleaning, the rule will only remove the files in that
	directory, but not the directory. The consequence of this policy is that
	there might be some remaining empty directories after cleaning all the
	content produced by ADA.</para>

	<para>To solve this issue, ADA offers one additional variable to be used
	in the <filename>Properties.txt</filename> file and is described, along
	with the rest of variables available, in the following table:</para>

	<xi:include href="VarTables/Cleaning_vars.xml"
		    parse="xml"
		    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>


	<para>The variable <code>clean.files</code> is used to specify those
	files or directories that are not properly removed by the implicit
	cleaning rules. Due to the danger of inadvertently deleting important
	files, this variable does not expand characters such as <quote>*</quote>
	or <quote>?</quote>. If you want to use it to delete multiple files that
	are not removed by the regular cleaning rules, you need to write all of
	their complete file names in the variable.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>
  </qandaset>
</section>
