<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="ADA_FAQ">
  <title>ADA Frequently Asked Questions</title>

  <section>
    <title>Installing ADA in Windows</title>
    <qandaset defaultlabel="qanda">
      <qandaentry>
	<question>
	  <para>What are the basic packages to run ADA in Windows?</para>
	</question>
	<answer>
	  <para>
	    ADA needs at least three packages to run in windows:
	  </para>

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>A Java Run Time Environment.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Ant: A Java based build tool. ADA relies on ANT to decide which
		documents to build and which tools to use for the task.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<ulink url="http://www.cygwin.com">Cygwin</ulink>: A linux-like
		environment for Windows.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	  
	  <para>
	    The first step then is to make sure you have a <ulink
	    url="http://java.sun.com/javase/">Java Run-Time Environment
	    (JRE)</ulink> properly installed.
	  </para>
	  
	  <para>
	    The second step is to download the <code>cygwin</code> installer a
	    program to select the packages wto install. Once started, the
	    initial page is shown in the following figure.
	  </para>

	  <informalfigure>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="images/CygwinSetUp.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	      <textobject>
		<phrase>Initial Cygwin Setup Program</phrase>
	      </textobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </informalfigure>

	  <para>
	    After starting the set-up program, you need to specify several
	    parameters to stablish a connection with a server. Keep advancing on
	    the installation steps until the screen to select the packages like
	    the one in the following figure is shown.
	  </para>

	  <informalfigure>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="images/CygwinSelectPackages.png"
			   format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </informalfigure>

	  <para>
	    Click in the botton with name <code>View</code> that appears above
	    the package list until the word <quote>Full</quote> appears to its
	    left. At that point, all packages suitable to be installed are shown
	    alphabetically ordered. From the list, you need to select
	    <emphasis>at least</emphasis> the following packages.
	  </para>

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<code>docbook-xml43 (or more recent)</code>: Docbook XML DTD
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<code>docbook-xsl</code>: XSL stylesheets for the DocBook XML DTD
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<code>git</code>: Fast version control system used to download
		the latest ADA version.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	  <para>
	    ADA is capable of using additional tools, but they are not essential
	    for the installation. The set-up program takes a few minutes to
	    download (through a net connection) all the required packages. This
	    step will take a few minutes and will depend significantly on the
	    speed of that connection.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    After all the required packages are installed, finish the execution
	    of the set-up program and start a Cygwin shell. This is usually done
	    by clicking on the icon that the set-up program has left on your
	    desktop or browsing through the program menu and selecting the
	    Cygwin executable. Once starte, a window like the one shown in the
	    following figure appears on the screen.
	  </para>

	  <informalfigure>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="images/CygwinShell.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </informalfigure>

	  <para>
	    The windows is a typical linux command interpreter that is ready to
	    received your orders. The first check that needs to be performed is
	    to make sure the Java Run-time Environment is properly installed. By
	    simply typing the command <code>which java</code>, if the answer is
	    a single path to a file with name <code>java</code>, the JRE is
	    properly installed. If the message states that no <code>java</code>
	    could be found, you need to review your Java installation.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    The third step is to install <ulink
	    url="http://ant.apache.org">Ant</ulink>. Ant is Java based, and
	    therefore, installing the application simply amounts to deploying a
	    directory and make sure that a couple of environment variables point
	    to the right locations.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    Once Cygwin has been installed, you have two choices: install Ant as
	    a regular windows application, or install Ant within Cygwin. The two
	    choices are very similar from the point of view of the installation
	    process, just unpack the zip archive in one location. The important
	    step is to set the environment variables ANT_HOME to point to the
	    new directory and PATH to include the <filename>bin</filename>
	    directory within Ant.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    Once you installed Ant, you may check the installation again with
	    the command <code>which ant</code>. As in the case of Java, if an
	    absolute path is shown, Ant is ready to execute. If not, you need to
	    review your installation procecure.
	  </para>
	</answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>
  </section>

<!--   <section>     -->
<!--     <title>Installing ADA in Linux</title> -->

<!--   </section> -->
</chapter>
