<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
  Copyright (C) 2008 Carlos III University of Madrid
  This file is part of the ADA: Agile Distributed Authoring Toolkit

  This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
  modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
  as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
  of the License, or (at your option) any later version.

  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
  GNU General Public License for more details.

  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
  along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
  Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  Boston, MA  02110-1301, USA.

-->
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<!--                                                              -->
<!--                    INSTALLATION IN WINDOWS                   -->
<!--                                                              -->
<!-- ++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++ -->
<section id="Installing_ADA_in_Windows"
         xreflabel="Top of the Section">
  <title>Installing ADA in Windows</title>
  <qandaset>
    <qandaentry id="requiredapplicationsinwindows">
      <question>
        <para>Which packages are needed in a Windows system before installing
	ADA?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>ADA needs some extra programs installed in your computer in order
        to work properly. The toolkit is installed using the version control
        system <command>git</command>. The minimum required packages to install
        (with their correspondign dependencies) are:</para>

        <itemizedlist id="tool_requirements">
          <listitem>
            <para><command>git</command>: Fast version control system used to
            download the latest ADA version.</para>
          </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><command>Python</command>: the interpreter and
	    libraries.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><command>python-lxml</command>: Python bindings for
	    <command>libxml2</command> and <command>libxslt</command>
	    libraries.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para><command>python-libxml2</command>: Python bindings for the
	    GNOME XML library.</para>
	  </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><command>docbook-xml</command>: Docbook XML DTDs.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><command>docbook-xsl</command>: XSL stylesheets to process
            DocBook.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><command>openssh-client</command>: SSH client program to
            connect to remote sites.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

	<para>TO REWRITE</para>

        <para>Aside from these three tools, ADA allows to process certain file
        types if some additional programs are installed. For example,
        translating figures from <ulink
        url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scalable_Vector_Graphics">SVG</ulink>
        to <ulink url="en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PNG">PNG</ulink> can be done using
        <command>Inkscape</command> but it needs to be properly installed and
        available for execution.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry id="how_to_install_python"
		xreflabel="Python has been installed">
      <question>
        <para>How to install Python in Windows?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>TO BE WRITTEN</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry id="howtoinstallpackages" xreflabel="How to install other packages">
      <question>
        <para>I got Java already installed, What else is required to run
        ADA?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>TO BE REWRITTEN</para>
        <para>Once <xref linkend="how_to_install_jre"/>, the next step is to
        download the <command>Cygwin</command> tool, a Linux-like environment
        for Windows. Once downloaded, the initial page of the installer is shown
        in the following figure.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry id="Fetch_ada_in_windows">
      <question>
        <para>All the required packages are installed. How do I install
        ADA?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>TO BE REWRITTEN</para>
        <para>Open a Cygwin shell and go to the directory where you want ADA
        installed (a directory with name <filename>ADA</filename> will be
        created. The computer needs to be connected to the net. Execute the
        command:</para>

        <programlisting id="git_install_command_windows">$ <command>git clone <xi:include href="Params.xml"
        xpointer="xmlns(xsl=http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform)xpointer(//*/xsl:param[@name='ADA_DOWNLOAD_URL']/text())"
        parse="xml"
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></command></programlisting>

        <para>A list of messages appear on the screen. After a while (depending
        on the speed of your net connection), the command terminates and a new
        directory with name <filename>ADA</filename> has been created containing
        all the required files.</para>
        <para>In order to make ADA available, the PATH environment variable
        needs to be modified by adding the path to the <filename>bin</filename>
        directory. You may follow the same procedure described in the <xref
        linkend="install_ant"/>.</para>

        <para>Once the environment variable <command>PATH</command> has been
        modified to include the <filename>bin</filename> directory within ADA,
        open a brand new Cygwin shell and type the following command</para>
        
        <programlisting>$ <command>which adado</command></programlisting>
        
        <para>As in the case of the <xref linkend="install_ant"/>, if the answer
        is a single path to the <filename>adado</filename> file similar
        to</para>

        <programlisting>/home/.../.../ADA/bin/adado</programlisting>
        
        <para>ADA is properly installed. If the message says <quote>which: no
        adado in (/usr/local/bin:/usr/bin:/....)</quote>, ADA is not available
        for execution and you need to review your installation.</para>

        <para>The final step to make sure that the commands provided by ADA are
        available is to <xref linkend="run_adacheck"/>.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry id="no_catalogs">
      <question>
	<para>TO REWRITE</para>
	<para>ADA takes a huge amount of time to process Docbook documents,
	why?</para>
      </question>

      <answer>
	<para>The symptoms for this problem is an unusually large amount of time
	for the toolkit to process a Docbook file. The process eventually
	finishes, but it takes for ever (in the order of minutes to process one
	or two files).</para>

	<para>The stylesheets in ADA import a set of default stylesheets to
	process most of the Docbook constructs. The location of these styleheets
	may vary from machine to machine. The way to solve this problem is using
	XML Catalogs. A catalog is a file specific for a single machine that
	specifies the location where certain files are installed. If this
	catalog is not properly deployed, <command>xsltproc</command> (the XSLT
	processor used by ADA) obtaines them all from the web. The number of
	stylesheets is high and therefore, processing time goes through the
	roof.</para>

	<para>	  Te solution for this problem is to make sure the packages specified in
	  <xref linkend="howtoinstallcygwin"/> are properly installed.
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry id="new_version_upgrade">
      <question>
        <para>A new version of ADA has been published, how do I upgrade?</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <para>ADA is distributed using the tool <command>git</command> which keeps
          track of the files you already have and the changes that need to be
          applied to upgrade to the latest version. The upgrade process
          requires simply to open a shell window, go to the directory where
          ADA is installed and execute the command:</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>git pull</command></programlisting>

        <para>The command will inform in some fairly cryptic way of the changes
          that are taking place. In principle, if the source files have not
          been modified, the change will go smoothly. If you have some
          personal modifications in the source files, you need first to tell
          <command>git</command> to store those changes. You need to execute
          the command:</para>

        <programlisting>$ <command>git commit -a -m "Your message here"</command></programlisting>

        <para>Try again to execute <command>git pull</command>. This time, the
          update process should go smoothly. There could be some conflicts
          when <command>git</command> tries to merge these changes with the
          ones you introduced. If such situation happens, it is called a
          <quote>merge conflict</quote> and it needs to be solved manually by
          the user. If you touched the source code of ADA, then we assume that
          you know how to solve merge conflicts.</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>
  </qandaset>
</section>

