<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<section lang="en">
  <title>
    <inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/compass_60x60.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject>
    The OpenACS Platform
  </title>
  <abstract>
    <para>
      The objective of this module is to understand the structure of the
      platform OpenACS/.LRN, the program it uses, how do they communicate with
      each other, where is the data store and how the server processes the
      requests to produce a web page.
    </para>
  </abstract>

  <section>
    <title>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/scenario_60x60.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
      Scenario
    </title>

    <para>
      The group works for the tech department of MediaCom Inc. The company needs
      a web platform to solve its intranet needs. The main functionality
      required is:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Typical operations in a highly interactive web platform: user
	  management, profiles, news, discussion forums, etc.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Be able to manage a large number of users.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Extensible with ad-hoc modules written by their own programmers.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Containing applications oriented toward virtual communities where
	  users may belong to multiple of them.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Capable to host all the material related to employee training.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      After studying the solutions available in the market, the company decides
      to use the platform <ulink url="http://www.openacs.org">OpenACS</ulink>
      and its extension for e-learning named <ulink
      url="http://www.dotlrn.org">.LRN</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
      This evaluation amounts to installing an instance of the platform (we
      recommend each team member to have one) study the available functionality
      and install an additional package created from scratch to see how feasible
      is to integrate a new functionality.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/strategy2_60x60.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
      Strategy
    </title>

    <para>
      To achieve this evaluation, the following steps are suggested:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Install an instance of OpenACS/.LRN for your personal use such that
	  you may stop/start the server quickly at will.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Get familiar with its functionality first from the point of view of
	  the regular user, no additional privileges, and then from the point of
	  view of the administrator.
        </para>          
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/resources_60x60.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
      Resources
    </title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  <ulink url="https://gradient.it.uc3m.es/xowiki/dotlrn_vm">VMWare
	  virtual machine with .LRN already installed</ulink>. It requires
	  downloading the <ulink url="http://www.vmware.com">VMWare
	  Player</ulink>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <ulink url="http://openacs.org/doc/current/index.html">OpenACS Core
            Documentation</ulink>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Blog <ulink url="http://www.dotlrn-experiments.blogspot.com/">dotLRN
            Develop Experiments.</ulink>. More precisely, the article entitle
          <ulink
            url="http://dotlrn-experiments.blogspot.com/2005/08/manual-instalacin-openacs-en-espaol.html">Manual 
            de instalaci칩n OpenACS en Espa침ol</ulink> and <ulink
            url="http://dotlrn-experiments.blogspot.com/2005/08/creacion-e-integracion-de-un-paquete_04.html">Creaci칩n 
            e integraci칩n de un paquete OpenACS en dotLRN</ulink>, that requires
	    the following zip file: <ulink url="documentacion.zip">Paquete de
            prueba</ulink>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <ulink url="http://openacs.org/xowiki">OpenACS Wiki</ulink>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/box_60x60.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
      Deliverables
    </title>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Show the execution of a new package with at least a modification
	  requiring the visualization of some data dynamically obtained from the
	  relational data base.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Upload in the <ulink
          url="https://gradient.it.uc3m.es/dotlrn/classes/master/master.platformsfornetworkedcommunities/platformsfornetworkedcommunities/file-storage/?folder_id=394176">Assignment
          area of the course</ulink> two HTML documents. One of them must
          contain the answer to the personal questions (one per team member) and
          the second must contain the answer to the group questions (thus one
          single document per group).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/questionmark_60x60.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
      Questions
    </title>

    <para>
      The following questions are grouped in two categories. Those that need to
      be answered individually, and those to be answered with a consensus within
      the team. All answers need to be written in an HTML document and uploaded
      to the Assignment area of the course.
    </para>

    <para>
      The questions requiring an individual answer are:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Describe the minimum set of tools and programs that are required to
	  install and execute correctly an instance of OpenACS/.LRN
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Describe the steps that are required to create a user account in the
	  platform.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Using a PostGreSQL client program (psql), connect to the database and
	  obtain the number of tables used by OpenACS/.LRN. Explain the steps
	  you followed.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
      The questions to be answered by the team are:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Explain what is the notification service offered by OpenACS/.LRN, how
	  can it be customized? What is it used for? Advantages and disadvantages.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Is is possible to change the distribution of portlets in the initial
	  user page? How about the number of portlets? Can the number of tabs be
	  modified in such page?
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
	  Propose a portlet that you think it is missing and can be useful for a
	  user in this platform.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	Complete the implementation of the demo with a page that uses a form and
	invokes the function <code>ad_form</code>. The form should receive data
	from the user and insert/delete/modify it in the data base. This
	deliverable needs to be shown in the last session of the module.
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</section>
